welcome to this evening's celebration of
25 years of prison legal news
my name is meg fiddler
i'm a civilian non-combatant
i'm not a lawyer
nor have i ever been a prisoner
i met and soon became friends with paul
wright 10 years ago
when he was awarded a fellowship by the
petra
foundation which i directed
the foundation honored petrotol shattuck
who grew up in germany in the shadow of
the third reich
came to this country to work as an au
pair
and stayed on to graduate from law
school with high honors
while raising a family and to devote her
life as a teacher
scholar lawyer and activist
to advancing human rights
when petra died young and suddenly in
the foundation was created to recognize
and encourage
unsung individuals who were making
distinctive contributions
to the rights and dignity of others
by taking risks and persevering without
the safety net of personal privilege or
institutional support
paul wright was named a petra fellow for
his extraordinary work from behind bars
for 13 years
on behalf of prisoners human rights and
civil liberties
in 1973
petra wrote
the problems i see in america are
fundamentally the problems of a mass
democracy
in which people have lost the feeling
that they can influence the government
and in which there's so much social and
racial conflict that it is very
difficult to make the old mechanisms
work
still she wrote i believe that if we
work to put our politics
to the test of our ideals and our values
which we spell out so clearly in the
constitution and the bill of rights
that there would be progress
and that's what we should struggle for
right now i'm honored to introduce
someone who has put his politics to the
test of those ideals and values
a friend of prison legal news tonight's
keynote speaker john kiriakou
john is a decorated veteran of cia
counterterrorism operations and the only
cia officer with the guts and integrity
to publicly confirm that waterboarding
was used to torture detainees in the
so-called war on terror
for upholding his sworn duty to support
and defend
the constitution of the united states he
served almost two years of a 30-month
prison sentence john
first i'd like to thank paul wright
i guess i knew paul wright
before i actually met paul wright
i arrived in in federal prison in loreto
pennsylvania
in february of 2013
and
after a day or two in prison i got a
nice note from paul wright
saying we have this publication it's
called prison legal news here's a
two-year subscription and i figured i
would be in prison about two years i
thought okay well that was nice i'll
send him a thank you note so i sent him
a thank you note
and then i sat down to read prison legal
news and prison legal news
literally changed
the course of my incarceration it it
changed the way i looked not only at my
own incarceration but at the issues of
mass incarceration and what a lot of
people myself included called the prison
industrial complex it opened my eyes to
issues that i otherwise would never have
been exposed to
issues as fundamental as those of of
civil liberties and human
rights i joked with paul
when we spoke in seattle a couple of
weeks ago that the first thing i would
do when my prison legal news arrived was
gather about a dozen different guys in
my cell
and we would read the news in brief out
loud i would read it out loud about
things that stupid prison guards around
the country have done
and gotten themselves into trouble and
we would sit and laugh and all these
stupid prison guards oh this one raped a
guy in the walk-in freezer and you know
so we would kind of make ourselves feel
better by
by
jumping on these prison guards but that
that was just for fun
prison legal news actually was very was
a very serious thing for me
because
it showed me what really was the most
important thing not just about the
publication but also about the
human rights defense center
i said in seattle that
i speak a lot all over the country and
i know my my topics well and so i
generally tend to wing it
i couldn't wing it with my seattle
address
and i didn't want to wing it with this
address either
and i was thinking to myself
why is it that i'm so much less
comfortable talking about this issue
and after thinking about it i realized
that it's because
this issue is so important and i think i
i hadn't really thought through why
prison legal news was so important to me
personally
the conclusion that i came to was that
it's important because when you're in
prison you really are all alone
i mean you may have friends and
relatives on the outside but in prison
life just stands still
and
it's like groundhog day where every day
is exactly like every other day it
doesn't matter if it's the middle of
july or if it's christmas your day is
going to be exactly like every other day
and you tend to forget
that life on the outside is continuing
to move forward
so it was prison legal news that made me
realize that there
is support out there for people like me
there there's an organization out there
that is writing
uh that is suing
uh that's pursuing activism
on issues that are that are important in
my day-to-day life
their lobbying
prison legal news and human rights
defense center really were
our voices on the outside
i can't tell you
how many people don't have confidence
in their own intellect
to be able to challenge either
their incarceration or the powers that
be that are that are doing things like
charging them 18 and 30 cents or
whatever it is for 10 minute phone call
for example
or giving them
a chase manhattan debit card with their
commissary money at the end of their at
the end of their incarceration but that
include fees that are so onerous
that really your commissary money is
going to end up going to chase manhattan
or to the bureau of prisons
but prison legal news understood
and prison legal news was out there
telling people what was happening
by way of background i was incarcerated
on a national security charge i was
charged actually with three counts of
espionage which is one of the gravest
crimes that an american can be accused
of when when we say espionage
we conjure up thoughts of julius knuffle
rosenberg
of of spying for a foreign country of of
treason
uh in some cases an espionage charge
carries with it the death penalty
i'm a patriot
i've always been a patriot and i took an
oath to uphold the constitution of the
united states
not to cover up the cia's dirty little
secrets
and so i decided in
in 19 uh i'm sorry in 2007 that
i was going to respond truthfully
to an abc news reporter's questions i
didn't know what he was going to ask me
i suspected that he would ask me about
torture and i i decided that if he did i
was going to tell the truth
and so in december of 2007 i gave an
interview to brian ross of abc news in
which i said three things that utterly
changed the course of the rest of my
life
i said that the cia was torturing its
prisoners
i said that torture was official u.s
government policy not the result of a
rogue cia officer
and i said that the president had
personally approved and signed of the
torture policy
i was immediately